<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exhortation to youth to prepare for judgment A sermon occasion'd by the late repentance and funeral of a young man. Deceased September 29. 1681.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214018</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826255</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826255</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60132)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1800:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exhortation to youth to prepare for judgment A sermon occasion'd by the late repentance and funeral of a young man. Deceased September 29. 1681.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.G. for Benjamen Alsop, at the Angel and Bible in the Poultry,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LXXXI. [1681]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Shower.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A funeral sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ecclesiastes XI, 9 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Young men --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Young women --  Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>An Exhortation to Youth to prepare for Judgment.</hi> A SERMON Occaſion'd by the Late REPENTANCE AND FUNERAL OF A Young Man, Deceaſed <hi>September</hi> 29. 1681.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ECCLES. I. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember now thy Creator, in the days of thy youth, while the evil days come not, nor the years draw nigh, when thou ſhalt ſay, I have no pleaſure in them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Benjamen Alſop,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> and <hi>Bible</hi> in the <hi>Poultry.</hi> MDCLXXXI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO John Bawdon <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF either the Preaching or publiſhing of the following Sermon; may be any way uſeful to promote the great deſign of doing good; if the ſeriouſneſs of the Subject, or the weight of the Inſtance that gave occaſion to it, may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken any one Soul to prepare for his final judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: I know you will heartily rejoyce and bleſs God with me; and as readily pardon my defects in the management of ſo important a Theme: and the rather, ſince I indeavoured only to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and perſwade an attentive Auditory, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting moſtly of young perſons) without the leaſt intention of appearing in Print; as knowing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, that what may be acceptable to a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ear, when pronounc'd from the Pulpit, doth often fail of being ſo, when perus'd afterwards by a critical eye. However, the Impreſſion once conſented to, I ought to addreſs it to no other <hi>name</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30652:3"/>but <hi>yours;</hi> being Conceiv'd and Born in your Houſe, as well as Preacht in your hearing; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when 'twas proper for me to prefix an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Connexion between ſeriouſneſs and chearfulneſs. For having diſcours'd ſomewhat concerning the <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Joy</hi> of a Chriſtian Life, as well as of the unreaſonableneſs and vanity of ſenſual pleaſures; it ſeem'd neceſſary to confirm that Truth by a lively Inſtance: And were there nothing elſe to recommend the practice of Godlineſs, but that tranquillity and peace of mind, that calmneſs and ſerenity of ſpirit which follows a good Conſcience, and is the only true ground of a chearful converſation; the argument were very preſſing. But I need not mention this, ſave to let you ſee the excellency of your choice, and thereby incourage others to make the ſame. And none, Sir, that underſtand my obligations <hi>to you</hi> and <hi>to your excellent Lady,</hi> will judge me guilty of the uſual flattery incident to ſuch Dedications; if I take this firſt opportunity to avow my Debt of Gratitude and Honour to you both. And ſuch I muſt profeſs it, as is exceeded only by the Duty ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Children to their <hi>natural Parents;</hi> my loſs of whom, your reſpects and kindneſs have in great meaſure undeſervedly ſupplied.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I have only to add, that as the mention of your <hi>Name</hi> will doubtleſs invite many to read the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> who would otherwiſe be apt to throw it by; ſo, I am told, I ſhall loſe other Readers, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing <hi>that</hi> of the perſon, on whoſe account <hi>it</hi> was Preacht. To which I have this to ſay, that his name and quality, his life and Converſation, the circumſtances of his ſickneſs, and his temper and expreſſions on his deathbed, are ſufficiently known; to obviate the leaſt inſinuation of a Forgery, as to what I have related concerning him. And as to what I have not recited, the Readers benefit would be as unconcern'd in the publication, as his curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity is like to be diſſatisfied, if he expect any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon of its concealment.</p>
            <p>I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Affectionate, Moſt obliged, Humble Servant, <hi>JOHN SHOWER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WE reckon it a piece of juſtice to the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of this <hi>Sermon,</hi> to believe, and (according to that belief) to teſtify, that the <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it ſelf</hi> did againſt his own inclination ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort from him the <hi>publication</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>For when the conflict was only between the <hi>Modeſty</hi> due (indeed) to his years <hi>on the one hand,</hi> and <hi>ſence of Duty</hi> on <hi>the other</hi> (upon the concurrence of a <hi>general</hi> Obligation, and a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcerned opportunity</hi> to promote the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal good of Souls) the determination of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>this way</hi> could not ſeem difficult to an impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, unbribed Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Whither the <hi>Diſcourſe it ſelf,</hi> the <hi>occaſion,</hi> and <hi>all circumſtances</hi> taken together have any aptneſs to ſerve that end, muſt be left to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch, as ſhall <hi>read,</hi> and conſider; with
<pb facs="tcp:30652:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom <hi>the Diſcourſe</hi> muſt ſpeak for it ſelf. And <hi>what it had reference to,</hi> will, we cannot doubt, appear not <hi>very conſiderable</hi> only, but be <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grateful</hi> alſo to all Pious and Good men. For tho' the Sermon import a relation to a <hi>Funeral,</hi> the Death of the Perſon had nothing in it ſo mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as his <hi>Repentance to Life</hi> will have with it of Satisfaction, and thanksgiving to God, with <hi>all,</hi> that are of a Serious, and Religious incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Nor can it enter into our thoughts, that any, to whom that Character belongs, will behold the inſtance of a Soul (as <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> will believe) <hi>reſcued out of the Snare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> and tranſlated to Eternal Bliſs with a <hi>ſlight,</hi> or much leſs with an evil eye; only becauſe it was not <hi>by their means,</hi> or not by one, in all things, <hi>of their mind and way.</hi> Or that what is the <hi>Joy</hi> of Angels, can be the <hi>Offence,</hi> and <hi>Grief</hi> of <hi>good men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſurely not poſſible, <hi>they</hi> can be ſo fatally divided between <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> as <hi>utterly to forget</hi> our <hi>higher common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> to <hi>Chriſt!</hi> For do we not all know, we were Baptized into <hi>his Name,</hi> and not of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> (imagined) head, or Maſter of a Sect?</p>
            <p>But though <hi>that tranſcendent Relation</hi> be not
<pb facs="tcp:30652:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>quite forgotten,</hi> there is too much cauſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, and lament that it is not remembred, and conſidered enough. And to reflect on it as <hi>one provoking cauſe</hi> of God's with-holding his Spirit, in ſo great part, from the Miniſtry of his word; and of the conſequent paucity of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and abounding wickedneſs of the time; that there is ſo great a proneneſs, in many, to ſubject the <hi>ſacred Miniſtry</hi> to the ſerving of ſome <hi>private mean deſign,</hi> more than that of the <hi>common Chriſtian Cauſe,</hi> and Intereſt; to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelite men to <hi>themſelves,</hi> rather than <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and make them more <hi>exact Formaliſts</hi> of their own Mould and Faſhion, rather than <hi>good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi> To teach them rather to <hi>deny</hi> or <hi>embrace</hi> this or that <hi>frame,</hi> and <hi>ſet</hi> of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> than to <hi>deny ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts, and to live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent World.</hi> And more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to inculcate, and preſs upon them the <hi>things wherein we differ,</hi> than the unſpeakably great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and more momentous <hi>things, wherein we are agreed;</hi> and whereof the Dead, Carnal, diſſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected heart of man far more needs the moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt inculcation.</p>
            <p>It may well be apprehended the <hi>Holy God</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30652:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>will be <hi>jealous</hi> in this caſe. And while we hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily joyn not, and do not accept and rejoyce in each others help and concurrence (though in ſomewhat different methods, which for the preſent we cannot give remedy to) in the purſuit <hi>of his ends,</hi> we have no reaſon to think it ſtrange, if he leave us to <hi>labour in the Fire,</hi> and weary our ſelves, to no purpoſe, in the purſuit of <hi>our own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us make it our buſineſs to recover as many Souls as we can to God; and when any are regain'd, and <hi>born anew</hi> (according to that <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Idea</hi> of having all Children taken for the Children of the <hi>Common-wealth</hi>) let us, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was the happy inſtrument, account they are neither <hi>mine,</hi> nor <hi>yours,</hi> but the Children of the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth of Iſrael,</hi> the Sons of God, and a part of the Redeemers Seed. How great will the common Joy be upon all ſuch occaſions! <hi>And God will rejoyce over us all, to do us good with all his heart, and with all his Soul,</hi> and to uſe us for the doing of much.</p>
            <p>His Co-operation and Bleſſing may then be cheerfully expected, when our united ſtrength and endeavour is aimed all one way; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to ends great and noble, worthy of God,
<pb facs="tcp:30652:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and which he will not diſdain, or count it diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and unfit to concur unto.</p>
            <p>It will ſurely one day come to this. Nor is it to be deſpaired of, but that <hi>the late work of God's Grace</hi> upon <hi>this young man</hi> (though ſince prematurely taken away) may be the earneſt and pledge of more, of the ſame bleſſed kind; and <hi>this Birth,</hi> part of the <hi>firſt Fruits</hi> of a Pious Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration to ſucceed; wherein <hi>Religion</hi> ſhall live, and be tranſmitted in greater rigour, to them that ſhall come after.</p>
            <p>Our hope lies moſtly among <hi>ſuch.</hi> And we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire you that are <hi>young,</hi> and in the prime of your age and ſtrength, ſeriouſly to conſider, how much the ſtreſs of a Religious Intereſt for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time in <hi>England</hi> depends upon <hi>you.</hi> Which that you <hi>may</hi> to better purpoſe; conſider alſo, how much <hi>you,</hi> more peculiarly, have of preſent hope in your own caſe. God hath a kindneſs for your Age; makes his firſt applications to you, at your entrance upon the common affairs, and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of humane Life, that you would <hi>then</hi> bethink your ſelves of him, as <hi>your Creatour,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider <hi>how</hi> you came into the World: whence it would not be difficult to collect <hi>for what.</hi> He covets the beginning of ſtrength, his Soul deſires
<pb facs="tcp:30652:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>firſt ripe fruits.</hi> And you have reaſon to be conſident, that what he <hi>ſeeks,</hi> he will <hi>accept,</hi> if you conſecrate them to him (as the <hi>firſt fruits</hi> were the ſacred devoted part.)</p>
            <p>Some of you may perhaps, already diſcern in your ſelves <hi>vicious inclinations,</hi> but your vices are not yet ſo <hi>deeply rooted,</hi> nor are ſo <hi>fixedly habitual,</hi> as theirs, who are grown old in Sin and eſtrangement from God. You have not ſo oft <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> his good <hi>Spirit.</hi> You have not reſiſted ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny checks of Conſcience, nor ſtifled ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions, as many others have.</p>
            <p>You have a merciful God to deal with. Thoſe are <hi>his own words,</hi> Prov. <hi>1.23.</hi> (and ſpoken more eſpecially to <hi>ſuch as you,</hi> as you will ſee, looking back to v. 4.) <hi>Turn ye at my reproof: behold I will pour out my Spirit to you.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that <hi>great God,</hi> the <hi>Maker and Lord of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth,</hi> you have been ſolemnly devoted. Conſider how <hi>great</hi> and <hi>awful names,</hi> the name of the <hi>Father,</hi> and of the <hi>Son,</hi> and of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> were in <hi>your Baptiſm,</hi> named upon you! You are as <hi>truly obliged</hi> hereby, as you are to <hi>your natural Prince;</hi> though, perhaps you have not, as yet, taken, <hi>in your own Perſons,</hi> the Oath of Allegiance. You would think it a reproach, and
<pb facs="tcp:30652:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>it would probably prove a ruin to you, to begin <hi>your courſe of commerce</hi> in the world, with <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Falſhood.</hi> Is it more <hi>Juſt,</hi> or <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> and <hi>Safe,</hi> to deal deceitfully with <hi>your God,</hi> than with <hi>men?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do not think he is to be leſs the object of your <hi>Love, Fear</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> for that you <hi>ſee him not;</hi> How many <hi>Subjects</hi> in <hi>England</hi> have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen the face of their <hi>King?</hi> and are they <hi>the leſs bound</hi> to be Loyal and Obedient? And how <hi>are you bound,</hi> but <hi>for the ſake of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Lord,</hi> and <hi>in him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have, not <hi>ſeen</hi> your <hi>own Soul,</hi> (or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you will call the <hi>vital Principle</hi> in you) which yet you are ſure you have; for can you not diſtinguiſh your <hi>living body</hi> from a <hi>dead?</hi> are you not ſure you live? and do you not <hi>love your own life,</hi> tho' you have not ſeen the very Principle it ſelf, which you live by? the <hi>God you have not ſeen</hi> is as near you. In him you <hi>live, move, and have your being.</hi> You have great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and obligation to <hi>ſeek the Lord,</hi> that you may even <hi>feel,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 17.</note> and <hi>find</hi> him out, who is ſo little <hi>far from any of you. You are his Ofspring,</hi> as the <hi>Holy Apoſtle</hi> tells you, in the words of an Heathen, that you might underſtand it to be <hi>no
<pb facs="tcp:30652:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>new, or ſtrange notion;</hi> but, even then, ancient and common. He is the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Parent</hi> of your <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Being.</hi> It is <hi>unnatural</hi> to affect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and ſtrangeneſs to <hi>your own Father.</hi> It is <hi>through the high excellency</hi> of his nature, that you <hi>ſee</hi> him not. And he is the object there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of your more <hi>excellent faculties.</hi> You have a <hi>mind</hi> capable of knowing him, and a <hi>will</hi> of chooſing him for your God, if they were made <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>aright</hi> directed towards him, which his <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> can ſoon effect in you, when you ſeriouſly ſeek, and rely upon them.</p>
            <p>'Tis of greateſt concernment to you to have <hi>his Favour,</hi> in <hi>whoſe Power</hi> you are, and in <hi>whoſe Hand your Breath is.</hi> And can you be exempt from <hi>his Power,</hi> who made you, and all things? if you doubt whether he <hi>can diſpoſe of you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> or <hi>puniſh</hi> you, was not the making of this World a greater thing? you cannot be ſo impoſed upon, if you uſe your underſtandings, as to be made believe, that it made it ſelf. For could you, if you were not, make your ſelves? and were it eaſier for all things, than for you?</p>
            <p>And you may <hi>ſenſibly perceive,</hi> if you will but reflect, and uſe your thoughts, that you are Subject to a Superiour, Over-ruling Power, that there is
<pb facs="tcp:30652:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>a Lord over you,</hi> and that you live not <hi>accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your own wills.</hi> For are you never <hi>ſick</hi> againſt your wills, or in pain againſt your wills? and do you not know you muſt one day dye, tho' you be never <hi>ſo</hi> unwilling? is it not better to have that mighty Lord <hi>your Friend,</hi> than your <hi>Enemy? in his Favour is life.</hi> And he is in a Redeemer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable to you. Read ſeriouſly, <hi>2 Cor. 5.17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Kingdoms and Nations are thrown into confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if he be diſpleaſed, and no courſe be taken for ſeaſonable reconciliation. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7.8.9, 10.</note> And can you ſtand before his anger? he hath long been <hi>England's God,</hi> your <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>your Forefathers.</hi> Do not you, in your own minds, eſteem that wiſe and ſage counſel, <hi>thy Friend, and thy Fathers Friend, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thou not.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.10.</note> How much more <hi>thy God, and thy Fathers God!</hi> It lies <hi>upon you,</hi> whether he ſhall continue the <hi>God of England!</hi> The <hi>paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal right</hi> derived unto young ones, <hi>continues</hi> the <hi>viſible relation,</hi> while their nonage laſts, and incapacity to treat and capitulate for themſelves. But can you think, <hi>when you are capable,</hi> your <hi>intereſt by your Parents</hi> can avail you any thing <hi>againſt your own perſonal rejection of God?</hi> No, <hi>not tho'</hi> Abraham <hi>were your Father,</hi> if
<pb facs="tcp:30652:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>you ſhould finally ſhew your ſelves rather <hi>a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers:</hi> Which we have great hope God will mercifully forbid.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Englands Youth</hi> ſhould <hi>generally</hi> (tho' not all at once, as they come not to be <hi>ſuch</hi> all at once) <hi>againſt their Baptiſmal Vow,</hi> caſt off God, here is an interciſion of the line, and an end of the relation between God and us. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you <hi>love your Country,</hi> you will <hi>love God,</hi> and ſtudy to pleaſe and <hi>ſerve him with your whole heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you love <hi>your Prince,</hi> you will do ſo; for would you have him to be (yea would you make him?) the Head of a deſtitute People, <hi>forſaken of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how would you propoſe to your ſelves to <hi>live your days,</hi> and ſpend your time in the World, without God? What, in eating, and drinking, and pleaſing your Fleſh till you dye? would you not take it for a ſcorn, and ignominy to you, if one ſhould tell you, you were born for no higher purpoſes? and are capable of no higher?</p>
            <p>But how dare you think, without <hi>knowing,</hi> and becoming <hi>ſpecially related</hi> to the <hi>God of your lives,</hi> of dying, and paſſing into <hi>an unknown
<pb facs="tcp:30652:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>World?</hi> Peruſe ſeriouſly the <hi>enſuing diſcourſe</hi> (that we longer detain you from it) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if it ſignifies any thing to your better preparation for <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Judgment;</hi> and (in Order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) to your holy, and more uſeful, comfortable life on Earth; It will anſwer the <hi>Authors De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> and <hi>(with his)</hi> the deſires and prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Affectionate Friends and Servants in our Lord.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>JOHN HOW. </item>
                     <item>V. ALSOP.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. l. 2. r. grateful, p. 11. l. 9. r. have right, p. 12. l. 29. dele did, l. laſt. r. of a, p. 17. l. 15. l. differences, p. 19. l. 23. ad ye, p. 21. l. 16. r. younger years, p. 24. l. 29. add to, p. 31. l. 2. dele and, p. 3. l. 7. r. exquiſite p. 32. l. 5. r. montentany.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30652:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Funeral-Sermon.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eceleſiaſtes XI. 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Rejoyce, o young man, in thy youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes: but know thou that for all theſe things God will bring thee into judgment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOtwithſtanding our manifold advantages for ſerious Religion in our younger years, and the contrary inconvenſences of deferring it to old Age or an indefinite hereafter; our frequent warnings by the death of others, to provide for our own, and the unſpeakable hazard of a ſick-bed Repentance; yet how apt are moſt perſons, in their youth and ſtrength, to forget their Creator and themſelves too! to indulge to carnal mirth and ſenſual delights; as ſuppoſing, by a fatal prejudice and miſtake, That obedience to God would introduce melancholly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the chearfulneſs of converſation, and ſpoil the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30652:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>of human life, and thereupon refuſe to beſtow a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thought about Religion and another World, till God by ſickneſs, or an haſty death, ſummon them to appear before his Bar: Upon which account it cannot be thought unneceſſary or unſeaſonable, upon all occaſions, to mind young perſons of their ſin and duty, their ſnares and dangers, their latter end and final judgment.</p>
            <p>What at this time directed my thoughts to ſuch a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is not unknown to divers preſent, <hi>viz. The death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Repentance of a young man lately deceaſed,</hi> who for ſome time paſt attended this Lecture, I hope; at length, with ſome ſeriouſneſs and profit, tho' at firſt he came only with a deſign to carp and ſooff, as with great remorſe he told me in his laſt ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if there be any now come hither upon the <hi>ſame</hi> errand, and with the <hi>ſame</hi> thoughts; I pray God <hi>command</hi> their attention; (for otherwiſe it would be in vain for me to <hi>beg</hi> it) and accompany his own Word with a powerful efficacy to their hearts, to convince their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and perſwade their wills, and awaken their Souls, that they may go away with other apprehenſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions than they came hither, as <hi>this deceaſed Penitent</hi> once did; whoſe Repentance and Funeral calls loudly to us all to conſider this Apoſtrophe of the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> in the Text, <hi>Rejoyce, o young man, in thy youth, and let thy heant chear thee in the days of thy youth, and walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes: but know thou, that for all theſe things God will bring thee to judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the coherence of theſe words with the preceeding Verſes, we need only obſerve, that <hi>Solomon</hi> in the former Chapters, having given many excellent rules for the quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our minds, and the comfort of our lives, under all that <hi>vanity</hi> which he pronounc'd upon this World, he
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30652:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>comes in this Chapter to exhort us to prepare for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For when all is done that can poſſibly be effected in order to a contented and a happy life; yet he tells us, that our life it ſelf is vain and tranſient, our death inevitable, and that <hi>the days of darkneſs will be many, verſ.</hi> 8. and then confutes that unreaſonable inference, which the young <hi>Epicure</hi> is too prone to make from ſuch premiſes; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding his fooliſh pretence and plea, by an <hi>Ironie:</hi> and yet endeavouring to awaken his Conſcience, by declaring the certainty of an after-reckoning, and by a ſolemn citation of him before Gods Tribunal. For to this purpoſe, we may ſuppoſe the young ſenſualiſt to retort the Argument,
<q>Are all things vain? Is life uncertain, and death and darkneſs near? let me then enjoy the light as long as I can, let me indulge my appetite and pleaſe my ſences, and gratify my luſts, and make the beſt improvement of this vain, this ſhort, uncertain life. Have I but a a little time in which to enjoy this world? Let me not make it ſhorter by a Stoical reſervedneſs; lot me not loſe this day, leaſt I never have another; but <hi>eat and drink for to morrow I may dye.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which ſuppos'd Objection, the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> anſwers, in the Words I have read, <hi>Rejoyce, o young man in thy youth, and let thy heart chear thee in the days of thy youth, q. d.</hi>
               <q>Let it do thee good, and bring thee joy, be as merry as thou canſt, and take all the ſatisfaction thy luſts can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; if thou think it beſt, and moſt adviſeable to do ſo. <hi>Walk in the ways of thy heart, and in the ſight of thine eyes.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>q.d.</hi>
               <q>Being reſolved upon a ſhort life and a merry, baulk nothing which thy luſt doth flictate; deny thy ſelf no thing thy fooliſh heart can wiſh, or thy ſenfual appetite may crave. But know for certain, a day of reckoning is at hand, when God will call thee to an account for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30652:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>thy ſenſual luſts and youthful follies: However now thou maiſt ſtifle the convictions of thy Conſcience by repeated debauches and lewd company; however now thou maiſt make a ſhift to drown the ſentiments of a reaſonable Soul by the noiſe of riot, or bring the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the <hi>fleſh</hi> to baniſh the preſaging fears of thy immortal <hi>ſpirit:</hi> however now thou maiſt flatter, or delude thy ſelf by the principles of a <hi>Sadducee,</hi> or pleaſe thy ſenſes by the practice of an <hi>Epicvre;</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>yet for all theſe things God will bring thee to judgment. q. d.</hi>
               <q>Whither thou wilt or no, a ſcrutiny ſhall be made into thy paſt actions, and an account muſt be given of thine ill ſpent life: and for all the vanities of thy <hi>youth,</hi> and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual pleaſures that now entice thee; God, a terrible and a righteous God will bring thee to his <hi>judgment-Seat.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And it follows, v. 10. <hi>Therefore remove ſorrow from thy heart,</hi> (by avoiding ſin, which is the cauſe of ſorrow) <hi>and put away evil from thy fleſh, for childhood and youth are vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the words may be collected theſe Three Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heads of Diſcourſe, as comprehenſive of the ſum of the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that <hi>Solomon</hi> makes uſe of an <hi>Ironie,</hi> and ſo in mockery and deriſion bids the young man <hi>rejoice,</hi> we may take notice, that <hi>ſinful mirth, and ſenſual pleaſure, is no real and ſubſtantial joy, fit for a wiſe man to chooſe.</hi> It hath but the <hi>appearance</hi> and the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>joy;</hi> for what is truly ſo, is nowhere to be had, without <hi>the fear of God, and the faithful keeping of his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In that he directs his diſcourſe to the <hi>young man</hi> in particular, we have a plain intimation; that <hi>young perſons of all others, are moſt apt to lay aſide the fear of God, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30652:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>forget their Creator, through the temptations of ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and youthful luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe he tells the <hi>young man,</hi> that even <hi>He muſt come to judgment,</hi> as an argument moſt proper to damp his car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mirth and jollity, and put a check to his purſuit of youthful Luſts. We may hence obſerve, in what reſpects <hi>the conſideration of a future judgment hath any force of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to perſwade young perſons to ſtop in their cours of ſin, and to remember their Creatour in the days of their youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt, I ſhall divide it into Two Branches, and ſo conſider. 1. <hi>That the carnal mirth of ſinners hath but the appearance and name of joy:</hi> being expreſt by an <hi>Ironie,</hi> while on the contrary, they meet with trouble and ſorrow, and diſſatisfaction in purſuit of their luſts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>the life of a ſerious Chriſtian, in the fear of God and the keeping of his Commandments, is the only chearful and merry life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. That <hi>ſinful mirth and ſenſual pleaſure hath but the appearance and name of joy.</hi> Doubtleſs the thought of Joy carrieth Argument with it to <hi>allure,</hi> as that of ſorrow to <hi>diſſwade;</hi> on which account we are commonly averſe to ſerious practical Religion in our younger years, as ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it would interfere with all the pleaſures of human life, and doom us to a perpetual mourning melancholick ſtate; whereas the <hi>Irony</hi> in the Text may let us know. That while we <hi>walk in the way of our own hearts, and in the ſight of our eyes,</hi> we deceive our ſelves with the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of Joy, and the <hi>name</hi> of Mirth.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, he <hi>bids</hi> the young man here <hi>rejoyce, and let his heart chear him;</hi> but it is in perfect ſcorn and deriſion, as knowing well that all his mirth and chearfulneſs muſt be falſe and ſpurious, vain and cauſleſs, leſs in <hi>quantity</hi> and worſe in <hi>quality,</hi> than the rejoicing of an upright Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30652:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>For as to ſenſual mirth, ſo greatful and infecting to the generality of youth, either it depends upon their Company, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.29.</note> which ſometimes begets quarrels <hi>and wounds without cauſe,</hi> or proves not ſuitable to their humour; or elſe ariſeth from a particular <hi>temper of Body,</hi> heighten'd by meats and drinks, and more than ordinary Diet; (and ſo hath more of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> than of the <hi>Man:</hi>) and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, muſt needs be of a ſhort continuance: or elſe is the ſole effect of youth, and ſo will undoubtedly decay as they advance in Age. However it is in it ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible and baſe, as feigned and not ſincere, as appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and not real, as vain and without foundation, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and without a cauſe: and not contemptible only in <hi>it ſelf,</hi> but likewiſe in relation to the <hi>Subject,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior part of Man: and much more in reference to the <hi>Object</hi> of their carnal mirth, when 'tis not only ſenfual, but forbidden too; and as truly ſo in regard of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> alſo, ſince it is eaſily diſturb'd, and quickly gone.</p>
            <p>How can it be imagin'd that a courſe of ſin can give a Man any ſolid mirth! when the Men themſelves are at ſuch a vaſt expence of care, and pains, and trouble, of unavoidable fear, and ſhame, and anxious thoughts; either to contrive, or to accompliſh, or to conceal their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed purpoſes and practices? ſo that I need not ask that queſtion concerning the <hi>joy</hi> of the <hi>Epicure,</hi> which <hi>Job</hi> doth of the <hi>Hope</hi> of the <hi>Hypocrite, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 27.8.</note> what is it when God ſhall take away his Soul?</hi> But in the mean time, what is it now? what mirth and joy have they for the preſent? who muſt rack their brains and ſtretch their fancies, and employ their moſt ſolicitous and concerned thoughts, how <hi>to make proviſion for their luſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.14.</note> and then muſt baffle their reaſons, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch their Conſciences, actually to enjoy them. For of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes a troubleſome Conſcience ſays ſo many rubs in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30652:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>their way, which they know not how to remove; ſtarts ſo many objections, which they cannot anſwer; makes ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doubts and Scruples, which they know not how to reſolve and overcome; that if they will venture upon the ſin, it muſt be even in deſpite of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Sometimes the very contrivance of their ſins gives them ſufficient uneaſineſs and trouble to ſpoil their mirth: ſuch previous thoughtfulneſs being neceſſary to frame the model, to fix the time, to deſign the manner, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the circumſtances of ſome impieties; and ſometimes the wickedneſs <hi>it ſelf</hi> is its own puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Look upon the young ſinner ſwelling in pride, or burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in luſt, or drowning in ſenſuality; conſider him rackt with impatient deſires, and burthen'd with unavoidable fears, leaſt his attempt be unſuccesful, or leaſt he be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed in the ſecrecy of the enjoyment, and his ſhame and folly publiſh'd to the world: And yet this is the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life of the ſenſual <hi>Epicure!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, when, by a cuſtom and continuance in ſin, the Devil is in full poſſeſſion, and Luſt upon the Throne; what <hi>Tyranny</hi> doth it exerciſe? and what a <hi>blind obedience</hi> muſt the ſinner yield? How often are you forced to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that you approve of that, which your mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns? how often do you ſubſcribe to that as true, which you know to be falſe? and ſo run headlong againſt the light of nature, and the checks of Conſcience, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render Soul and Body and all, to the will of Satan, and the command of an imperious, domineering Luſt?</p>
            <p>Now, what mirth or joy can conſiſt with ſuch a ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude? yea, while you <hi>weary your ſelves to commit iniquity,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.5.</note> what frequent vexations do you meet with from the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment of your hopes, finding ſorrow, where you look'd for joy; an offenſive ſtench inſtead of a perfume;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30652:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>and a noiſom weed in the room of a flower? Still ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, and further, is thought neceſſary to your contentment, and ſatisfaction, and joy, than what you poſſeſs already: either the <hi>preſence</hi> of ſomewhat which you cannot obtain, or the <hi>abſence</hi> of ſomewhat, which you cannot get rid of, or the <hi>continuance</hi> of ſomewhat, which is not in your power to keep, or ſuch a <hi>change</hi> and variety, as you cannot accompliſh: And muſt this be concluded the only merry and joyful life?</p>
            <p>Moreover, Let a man but ask you on the <hi>morrow,</hi> what is become of the pleaſure of the <hi>laſt nights</hi> debauch? when there remains nothing but a ſting in the Conſcience; Where <hi>then,</hi> I pray is your mirth and joy? For when once the heat of your Wine and Luſt is over, and you dare take the liberty of ſober thoughts, a guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will then tell you <hi>your own,</hi> and you ſhall hardly be able to ſtop its mouth. And tho' in part you may have waſh'd away the ſenſe of former <hi>drunkenneſs</hi> by more <hi>Wine:</hi> or think to drown the voice of your boſome enemy, the accuſer within, by running into jovial Company, and an exceſs of riot; yet ſome ſmart affliction, or ſome ſharp reproof, or ſome ſerious Sermon, may ſet your ſins in order again, and make your wounds to bleed afreſh: And then <hi>Conſcience</hi> (notwithſtanding your endeavours to ſtop its mouth, and ſmother its accuſations) will not fail to laſh the <hi>Drunkard,</hi> and ſtone the <hi>Adulterer,</hi> and make the Lips of an <hi>Harlot</hi> bite like a <hi>Cocatrice.</hi> You <hi>ſhall</hi> hear its voice, and underſtand its errand, and feel a mortal qualm upon your ſpirits, from ſuch convictions as you cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſtifle.</p>
            <p>But if this be not the caſe of <hi>all,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſome</hi> are given up to a <hi>Reprobate ſenſe;</hi> yet how often on aſick-bed doth the agitation of their own diſturbed thoughts ſet all in a flame
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30652:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>within. When the <hi>remembrance</hi> of their <hi>drunken</hi> exceſſes gives them Vinegar and Gall to <hi>drink,</hi> and makes them once more ſick; from that terrible thought, that for ought they know the next draught may be of the <hi>Cup</hi> of God's Eternal Wrath in the Lake of Hell. When the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their luſtful <hi>heats</hi> gives them the ſad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and <hi>preludtum</hi> of unquenchable <hi>Fire,</hi> into which they are ſinking. When the <hi>eccho</hi> of their Oaths and blaſphemies (which <hi>ſtuck</hi> thro' the Name of God) ſhall <hi>peirce</hi> their Souls with an intolerable remorſe. When a ſad reflection on their paſt prophaneſs, in ſcoffing at what is Serious and Holy, in ridiculing Religion, and making a mock of Sin, ſhall put them into a fit of trembling, from the unavoidable fears of a Judgment to come. Now if this be the <hi>ordinary</hi> ſtate of their caſe, as moſt certain it is, well might the <hi>wiſe man</hi> expoſe their mirth to ſcorn, and by an <hi>Ironie</hi> give them leave to rejoyce.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Joy of a Righteous, Holy Perſon, in the fear of God and the keeping his Commandments is the only true and proper Joy.</hi> And the Life of an upright Chriſtian, the only chearful and merry Life.</p>
            <p>Whereas ſome men have inferr'd, that becauſe there is a <hi>Woe</hi> pronounc'd in Scripture to thoſe that <hi>laugh,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 6.25. <hi>Matt.</hi> 4.5.</note> and a <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> to thoſe that <hi>mourn</hi> and <hi>weep:</hi> that it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary, if we will be ſerious Chriſtians, that we muſt be ſad and unſociable, melancholy and dejected, and lead a life of continual complaints and ſorrows. They might as well conclude a neceſſity of turning Monks or Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, becauſe the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>it is eaſier for a Camel to paſs through the eye of a needle,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 16.24</note> than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> For as to that part of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Life, which conſiſts in the <hi>contemplation</hi> of ſpiritual things, the infinite excellency and novelty of the <hi>objects</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30652:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt render it pleaſant. And as to that, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in <hi>practice,</hi> it muſt needs be more ſo; from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging Teſtimony of a good Conſcience, and the Joy of the Holy Ghoſt; unſpeakably more delightful and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory, than the moſt raviſhing pleaſures the <hi>Epicure</hi> can boaſt of. The beſt of <hi>his</hi> being ſhort and tranſient, and mixt with ſome uneaſineſs and trouble. But the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of an Holy Soul, are pure and ſubſtantial, durable and laſting, riſing higher and increaſing more by the very injoyment: not eaſily interrupted by a change of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Circumſtances and Conditions in the World, nor broken on a ſudden by little accidents that befal us una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares; which is not to be deny'd in reference to ſenſual Joy.</p>
            <p>Sirs, who is it, that either is or can be Joyful, that actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally is ſo, or hath reaſon to be ſo? If not the upright obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient Chriſtian?</p>
            <p>Is not the continual preſence of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Father Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and the conſtant Miniſtry and Attendance of his bleſſed <hi>Angels,</hi> a ground of Joy? He may then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. Is not peace with God, and peace with Conſcience, and peace with the whole Creation? Is not Redemption from the bondage of Sin, from the ſlavery of the Devil, from the ſting of Death, and the curſe of the Law, and Gods Eternal Wrath, enough to make him chearful? He may then rejoyce.</p>
            <p>If the favour of God, and the acceptance of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſervices with him, be ſufficient reaſon to diſſwade from ſadneſs; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecol.</hi> 9.7.</note> they may then <hi>eat their Breadwith Joy,</hi> and <hi>drink their Wine with a merry heart, for God accepteth both them and their work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If freedom of acceſs to the Throne of Grace; if a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of being granted in what ſo e're they ask; if the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30652:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>aſſurance from a God, that cannot lye, that all things ſhall work for good; If to dwell in his houſe, and ſit at his Table, and be related to him as a Father; if to hear his Word, and ſing his Praiſe, and receive the Communications of his Grace, the pledges of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Love, and the comfortable foretaſts of Everlaſting Joy, be enough to make them <hi>Chearful,</hi> They, and they only <hi>right</hi> have to be ſo: And that in <hi>Every Condition.</hi> Are they reproacht and ſlander'd? they may yet be chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe God <hi>will bring forth their Righteouſneſs as the Light, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.6.</note> and clear their Integrity as the noon-day</hi> Are they afflicted, by poverty, or ſickneſs, or diſapointments in their deſigns and hopes? they may yet be chearful, and thank God for all the advantage and benefit of his wiſe diſpenſations of providence. Are they Tempted by the Devil? they may yet be <hi>Chearful; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> becauſe God will ſhortly tread Satan under their feet, and not permit them to be tempted above what their able.</hi> Do they ſuffer for Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſake? they may yet be Chearful; yea, <hi>rejoyce</hi> and <hi>be exceeding glad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2.</note> and <hi>count it all Joy</hi> to receive ſuch an honour. For there are promiſes, perticularly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to ſuch a ſtate, ſufficient to encourage them; yea, to make them rejoyce. Do they ſometimes Mourn with a <hi>godly ſorrow?</hi> yet may they ſtill rejoyce, ſince to conſider the end and effect of that ſorrow, will give it a mixture of Joy: And even their penetential tears do but clear their eyes to look up to Heaven with delight and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and enable them the better to read a pardon.</p>
            <p>And here it were eaſy to ſhew how their Faith, and hope, and love, how their humility, meekneſs, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, their contentedneſs with God's allotment, their reſignation to his Will, their ſatisfaction in his Choyce, their well pleaſedneſs with his Order, their preparedneſs for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30652:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>every Condition, their diligence in their callings, their moderation in the uſe of lawful things, and their inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and harmleſneſs in their carriage and behaviour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others, do all contribute to a chearful and a joyful life. Therefore well might the Pſalmiſt tell us that <hi>the Righteous ſhall be glad in the Lord, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.10.</note> and all the upright in Heart ſhall Glory.</hi> And well might our Lord adviſe his Diſciples not to be lifted up with the gift of Miracles, but <hi>rejoyce rather that their names were written in Heaven.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.20.</note> And well might the Apoſtle command Chriſtians to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce</hi> (not by an <hi>Ironie,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> here ſpeaks to the Young Man, but) in the moſt real and proper ſenſe, <hi>Rejoyce in the Lord always, yea, and again, I ſay rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much for the firſt General.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Let us conſider, in that the Wiſe-man directs his diſcourſe to the Young Man in perticular, we have thence a plain intimation, that <hi>of all others, young perſons are moſt apt to neglect the fear of God, and be unmindful of their Maker through the temptation of ſenſual pleaſures and youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful luſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' God demand his right as ſoon as we are capable of underſtanding it; and to ſerve the Lord from our youth is but juſt and reaſonable, conſidering that ſo great a part of our life is already cut off by our Infancy and Childhood; tho' the longer we delay, the greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty ſhall we meet with, when ever we ſet about it; tho' our whole life at longeſt (as ſoon as we are capable and as long as we did live) ſhould be devoted to God, and 'tis all little enough, if we conſider its relation to our Eternal State; tho' the ſooner we begin, the more welcome we ſhall be, and the more acceptable our Obedience; yea, tho' an <hi>Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> piety be the only hopeful method to prevent the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of a ſudden death, and the terrible reflections of old age, and the intolerable pangs a death bed remorſe; yet ſuch
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30652:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>is the power of Original. Sin in young perſons; ſuch, and ſo many are the ſnares of youth; and thoſe ſo agreeable to their vicious inclinations; ſuch the force of prejudice; Such the artifices of the Devil; and ſo prevalent the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions of evil Company; they are uſually ſo proud, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and unexperienced, ſo raſh, haſty, and unadviſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſo eaſily infected with Sadduciſm and the principles of Infidelity, ſo loth to aſſent to any ſuch premiſes, whoſe con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion will infer the neſſeſſity of changing their preſent courſe, that they of all others do moſt need a ſerious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to remember their latter end and final Judgment, leaſt through the temptations of Senſual mirth and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, they <hi>put the evil day far from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For (alas!) how ſeldome do we conſider in Youth what we are! and why we were made! or what is our buſineſs in the World! and what will be the end of our preſent courſe! Whereas one thought of God and our laſt Judgment, methinks, ſhould be enough to <hi>drown</hi> all other thoughts as the noiſe of a <hi>Canon</hi> doth that of a <hi>Whiſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Senſe is ſo prevalent, and Reaſon ſo weak, we are ſo much inclined to the one, and ſo unwilling to be led by the other, that roys and trifles, ſports and recreations, and the vanities of fools and Children poſſeſs our hearts, and employ our time, not looking <hi>behind</hi> us, to what we have either done, or been; nor before us, whither we are going, and what in all likelyhood will be the period of our preſent mirth, and the ſad <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of our Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful luſts.</p>
            <p>Young perſons will hardly be convinced, but that Now is their ſeaſon to be brisk, and Jovial, having time (as they count) to command, and the World before them; that it is time enough to think of Death when they are arreſted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30652:16"/>by ſickneſs, or <hi>wither'd</hi> by old Age; let them be concerned about another World, who are leaving this; their bloed now is warm, and their Spirits nimble, their ſenſes are quick, and their paſſions ſtrong; they will <hi>walk in the way of their own hearts and in the ſight of their eyes;</hi> and ordinarily ſplit upon that Rock of Evil company, where ſo many thouſand Veſſells at their <hi>firſt launching out</hi> have daſht in pieces. Beſides, their Age is moſt inviting to the Devil to bend his chiefeſt forces againſt them, rather than againſt Children, or Aged perſons? the <hi>former</hi> not being capable of making a choice, and the <hi>latter</hi> being fix'd and reſolv'd in their way; his principal endeavours therefore are levell'd againſt Youth, to draw off their hearts from God and Holy things, and to divert their thoughts from the conſideration of Death and Judgment, which would otherwiſe reſtrain and check them in purſuit of their luſts: And this brings me to the Third General, to conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That for all theſe things God will bring us to Judgment.</hi> And therein what <hi>Arguments</hi> the thoughts of a <hi>future Judgment</hi> may rationally ſuggeſt <hi>to damp the carnal mirth of young perſons,</hi> and perſuade them to <hi>remember their Creatour in the days of their youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to inforce this Argument I might here mind you of the miſchief you will do to others by an ill example, and of the aggravation of your ſin by employing the beſt of your time in the ſervice of the Devil, which muſt needs make judgment more terrible, in that your final doom, the conſequences of it will be more ſevere.</p>
            <p>I might tell you the ſooner you repent, the more hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful is your caſe in reference to a pardon; I might large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſcribe the happy influence of an early Piety with reſpect to the future part of our lives, to direct our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30652:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>choice, and govern our actions, and prevent a great deal of Sin, and ſhame, ſorrow, and repentance; I might mention the comfortable reflections in Old Age upon a well-ſpent life; our capacity of greater Service to God now; and our aſſurance of a weightier crown of Glory hereafter; with all the other conſiderable benefits that have reſpect either to a ſafe and happy life, a comfortable Old Age, and a peacable Death, or a joyful Reſurrection, and a bleſſed Eternity; all which will come under the Argument in the Text; and what I ſhall ſay of it may be compriz'd under the following particulars,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let young perſons conſider, that notwithſtanding their preſent mirth and jollity, yet the <hi>Judgement of God is infallibly certain.</hi> It is an unqueſtionable, undoubted truth, that <hi>for all theſe things God will bring thee to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, that this Judgment is <hi>near at hand,</hi> and will <hi>ſhortly</hi> take place.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider your ſummons may be <hi>ſuddain,</hi> before you are aware.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, that Youth and health is the <hi>fitteſt time to prepare for this Judgment of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That if through the temptations of carnal mirth and youthful luſts you neglect your preparation, it is more then probable <hi>your paſſage by death to this Judgment of God will be very uncomfortable and full of horrour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That <hi>this Judgment it ſelf, and its immediate conſequences, will be intollerably dreadful to unprepared Sinners, whether Young or Old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, that notwithſtanding your preſent mirth and jollity, yet <hi>this final judgment is infallibly certain.</hi> What is here affirmed concerning <hi>perſons,</hi> is aſſerted likewiſe concerning <hi>things</hi> in the next Chapter, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>that God will bring every work
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30652:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>into Judgment, with every ſecret thing whither it be good, or whither it be evil.</hi> Methinks I need not tell you, that the Doctrine of this final Judgment is declar'd in Scripture with the greateſt plaineſs, confirm'd by the ſtrongeſt Evidence, and preſt upon the Conſcience with the moſt cogent, and inforcing and Arguments; eſpicially ſince the pretended Objections on the behalf of the <hi>Sadducee,</hi> and the ſenſual <hi>Epicure</hi> are ſo weak and trifling, that if their <hi>lusts</hi> were not ſtronger than their <hi>arguments,</hi> they <hi>themſelves</hi> would be aſhamed to offer them.</p>
            <p>For whoever disbelieves a future Judgment muſt either conclude that the <hi>Almighty God cannot,</hi> or <hi>that the Righteous God will not</hi> call us to an account for what we have received and done, tho' his abſolute <hi>Omnipotence</hi> doth aſſure us, that he <hi>can,</hi> and his invariable <hi>truth</hi> (having declared his purpoſe) that undoubtedly he <hi>will,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And do we think that all the aſſurance of this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God; which the Scripture gives us that all thoſe plain aſſertions concerning the Judge himſelf, and the perſons to be Judged, and the conſequence of the Judgment, and the certainty of it, that they are only <hi>terms of art</hi> to affright the world, and not real intended truths, which will take effect according to their natural meaning; that the whole account is perfect <hi>fiction,</hi> and meer Romance, contriv'd on purpoſe to keep the World in due <hi>Decorum,</hi> and ſo to prevent ſome bad effects only in reference to the preſent State of things, which would probably follow, if this belief did not obtain; Whereas is it not neceſſary, that there ſhould be a Judgment day, for the conviction and condemnation of great Sinners, that ſcorn the Legiſlative authority of God, and trample on his Government, and are above the check and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roul of humane laws? (to manifeſt the Righteouſneſs of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30652:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>God, as Ruler of the world, in rendering to every man according to his works and to uphold the honour of his wiſe Government, whereof Judgment is as neceſſary and eſſential a part as Legiſlation; the latter without the former being little elſe than ſhew and mockery; is it not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the vindication of Religion from that contempt and ſcorn, that is powr'd upon it; Is it not neceſſary to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riddle the myſteries of Divine Providence, and diſcloſe the ſecret wickedneſs of Hypocrites, and put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between thoſe that ſerve him, and thoſe that refuſe to do ſo? As likewiſe to rectify the miſtakes and falſe opinions, that are abroad in the world concerning God, and Chriſt, and Holineſs, and Sin, to put an end to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, and determine the difference concerning what is Truth and what is Error? Theſe and ſuch like things conſidered (beſides the Authority of Divine writ) do <hi>morally aſſure</hi> us, that there will be an after-reckoning, and a final Judgment. And methinks one thought of the certainty thereof, ſhould give a check to your c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mirth, and caſt a damp upon your Senſual joy, and abate your heat and vigour in a courſe of Sin. For did we but believe that for all theſe things God will bring us to Judgment, how could we ſo readily entertain the temptations of the Devil, and fall ſuch an <hi>Eaſy prey</hi> to his devices? How could ſo many unhappy <hi>Youths</hi> invade their own Damnation, and ſnatch it as it were out of the hands of Juſtice? thruſt away their preſent and future happineſs, and fly into the Devils, arms in the perſult of their youthful luſts, tho' they have been told ſo plainly, and warn'd ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of a Future Judgment? How could theſe things be? if they did but believe the certainty of this final judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? and how dreadful will be their caſe who are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd till they find it to be ſo who will not acknowledg
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30652:18"/>this Judgment of God, till they know the dreadfulneſs and terrour of it, by being brought to their Trial; who will not believe that God will ever call them to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, till a final Impenitence, joyn'd with their Infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, bring them under his condemning Sentence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider, that <hi>this Judgment is near at hand</hi> and <hi>will ſhortly take place.</hi> As Death will conſign us over to God's Tribunal; ſo childhood, and youth, manhood, and old age, are but ſeveral ſtages that haſten us to Death. Yet a little while and we muſt <hi>go the way of all living:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 16.22.</note> How concern'd and thoughtful ſoever now we are about this World, we muſt ſhortly bid adieu, and take our leave. Even the Man of <hi>buſineſs</hi> muſt find a <hi>time</hi> to dye, and give an account of his Stewardſhip; tho' he allow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>little</hi> or <hi>none</hi> to prepare for Death and Judgment. Our <hi>Youth</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> is quickly gone, we ſoon decline and languiſh into Duſt: Aſſoon as we begin to live, we are haſtening to the end of our Life. As a Candle, aſſoon as it begins to burn, or an hour glaſs aſſoon as it is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, doth haſten to its end: (our life withering like a <hi>Flower,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.4.</note> and paſſing like a watch in the night.) We muſt dye ſhortly, and much ſooner than they who lived in the firſt ages of the World. As Death is the certain conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>old age;</hi> ſo <hi>thoſe Evil days</hi> (as the wiſe Man calls them) do ſtill <hi>draw near,</hi> and will quickly overtake us. Whether we eat, or drink, or ſleep; whether we be ſad or merry; whether we talk or are ſilent; whether we work or are idle; whether we are ſtudious or careleſs; whether we prepare for Death and Judgment, or whether we deſpiſe and avoid ſuch Thoughts: And yet how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſpend ther youthful days in vanity and ſin, with a careleſs neglect of God and their Salvation, <hi>in gluttony
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30652:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Drunkenneſs, in Chambering and wantonneſs, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.13.14.</note> not putting on the Lord Jeſus, nor walking in his Spirit; but making pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof.</hi> As if this day of the Lord were a great way off, at a mighty diſtance: Whereas our Judge is at the door, and the end of all things doth approach, and it can't be long ere all the World muſt receive their Doom.</p>
            <p>A beleiving thought of <hi>this,</hi> would certainly imbitter the pleaſures of ſin, would quench our fond deſire, and check our Fooliſh hopes, and ſpoil the reliſh of our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Joy; would blaſt the Beauty, and darken the luſter of worldly greatneſs; would ſadden the delights, and weaken the Temptations of fleſhly pleaſures. For what ſatisfaction can that man take in Jovial Company, in the paſtimes of Children, and the laughter of Fools, who is verily perſwaded, that ere long he muſt appear to <hi>Judgment?</hi> How can he be enamour'd of this <hi>Earth,</hi> and after ſerious deliberation be fond of outward gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure; who beleives, and knows, that ſhortly the <hi>Earth</hi> it ſelf <hi>ſhall be burnt up,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10.</note> the Trumpet of the Arch Angel found, and our Glorious Judge ſummon all Man-kind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Bar, by that Thundring Voice, <hi>Ariſe dead and come to Judment?</hi> And can we grant this <hi>day of the Lord,</hi> to be not only certain, but <hi>near</hi> at hand; and not think it time to prepare for our ſolemn appearance? ſhall we contradict our principles, and live in a repugnancy to our avowed Creed, under the plain cenſure of Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Hypocriſy</hi> or folly? The <hi>Firſt</hi> from our profeſſion, if we do not beleive it; the <hi>Second</hi> from the unſuitableneſs of our practiſe, in caſe we do.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, <hi>that your Summons to this Judgment of God may be ſudden and unexpected, and overtake you unawares.</hi> When God will require your Souls to appear before his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30652:19"/>Tribunal; how ſoon or ſuddenly he will do it, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay. The <hi>time</hi> and <hi>place</hi> of our Death, in kindneſs and wiſdom, is concealed from us, that we may <hi>every where</hi> ſtand upon our gaurd, and <hi>every moment</hi> expect our call to Judgment: becauſe we know not whether God by ſickneſs will advertiſe us of our approaching end, or his ſtroke be ſudden by an unexpected caſualty. And therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaking to the <hi>Jews,</hi> as to one man, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 30.20.) ſaith he of God, <hi>He is thy Life, and the length of thy Days. q d.</hi> The ſhortning or prolonging of thy days is in the Hand of God. Hence ſome are taken the firſt hour, and ſome at the third, and ſome at the ſixth, and ſome at the ninth, and others let alone till the eleventh; but that is a great <hi>uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty:</hi> for we may be ſurpriſed. Innumerable accidents attend us every where, that may blot our names out of the <hi>Book of Life,</hi> and ſuddainly confine us to the Chambers of Death. It may be <hi>this day</hi> we are Jovial, and in health among our friends, and worldly affairs: and <hi>to morrow</hi> arreſted with a Summons to Judgment. In the <hi>morning</hi> in chaſe of earthly honour, riches, or delights: and in the <hi>Evening</hi> laid out for our funeral, by various acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents not now foreſeen by us or any of our friends.</p>
            <p>We <hi>may</hi> be cut off while we preſume on hereafter, while we reſolve to repent, in the midſt of our holy purpoſes, before they are performed: For tho' we read in Scripture of the <hi>Sinner of an Hundred years old, that he ſhall be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſt;</hi> yet have we no example of <hi>one in</hi> a thouſand, that lives to that age. <hi>This young perſon,</hi> whoſe funeral occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd my diſcourſe, not many days ſince was as ſtrong and healthful, and as likely to Live as any of us; and 'Tis a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great queſtions, whether <hi>you</hi> and <hi>I</hi> may have ſo much Time and Space to repent upon a <hi>Sick-bed</hi> as <hi>he</hi> had, who enjoy'd his ſenſes and the uſe of his reaſon to the very laſt. <hi>This day</hi> therefore cannot be too ſoon to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30652:19"/>becauſe to <hi>morrow</hi> may be too late: Every unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Sinner being expos'd to as many hazards of Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſtruction, as their may be accidents to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize 'em with ſudden Death.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Conſider, that <hi>youth and health is the fitteſt time to prepare for this final judgment:</hi> As to the <hi>former,</hi> if we but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on the manifold infirmities of old age, that weakneſs of body, and that decay of parts which doth uſualy accompany that ſtate, the hardning of their hearts by a cuſtome and continuance in Sin; the loſs of memory and quick apprehenſion; the want of thoſe vigorous Affections, and flexible inclinations which they had in Youth; which makes it more difficult to convince and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them; ſuch conſiderations as tkeſe, methinks ſhould be enough to diſcourage a delay in our young yerears.</p>
            <p>But beſides this, how can ſuch perſons expect to find' acceptance with <hi>God</hi> in the dregs of their time! after the miſſpending of an whole Life to <hi>his</hi> diſhonour? for tho I would not diſcourage their utmoſt endeavours, and thro' the mercy of God in Chriſt, there is hope enough to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a total diſpair; yet what can we ſuppoſe ſhould be the ſubſtance of ſuch a mans prayer, but to this effect?</p>
            <p>
               <q>Lord, I have waſted my days in ſin, and ſacrificed the flower of mine age to ſport and folly, to the provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy Juſtice, and the hazard of my Salvation; the beſt of all my Time, I muſt needs confeſs, hath been devoted to the will of Satan, and devoured by my Luſts: But I here preſent thee with the Lees and refuſe of my ſtrength and Age, the little fragments, and poor remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they have left; I beſeech thee, for the ſake of Chriſt to receive me now at laſt, tho' I did obſtinately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny obedience to thy earliar calls, and wilfully refus'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſooner: tho' now my ſtrength, as well as my body, is bow'd down to the Grave, and I am hardly capable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30652:20"/>of doing thee any Service: denyme not, O Lord, <hi>to live with thee</hi> in the <hi>other World,</hi> tho' I have liv'd ſo <hi>long without thee in this.</hi>
               </q> What prevalency do we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine there can poſſibly be in ſo <hi>weak an addreſs?</hi> without a Soverain extraordinary Grace to relieve the exigence of ſuch ſad and diſcourageing Circumſtances?</p>
            <p>And then as to <hi>health,</hi> that for certain is the moſt <hi>proper time</hi> to prepare for Judgment: Let us but ſuppoſe the young ſinner ſeiz'd by a fit of Sickneſs, if the accuteneſs of the diſeaſe do not influence the brain, and and cauſe a <hi>dilirium;</hi> yet is <hi>that</hi> a time to repent, and make your peace with God, and provide for our appearance before his judgment Seat? for uſually the underſtanding is then clouded, the fancy then diſturb'd, the paſſions diſordered, and the thoughts diſtracted.</p>
            <p>Conſider ſeriouſly, what is wont to be the hurry of a violent diſtemper; ſuppoſe reſtleſneſs, through heat, or pain, or want of ſleep: or ſuppoſe the Phyſician ſhould miſtake thy caſe: or the Devil uſe his ſubtelty and malice to deceive or terrify thy guilty Soul; and then tell me, whether a <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed</hi> be a fit ſeaſon to prepare for <hi>Judgment?</hi> May not thy thoughts have work enough to ſtruggle with thy pains? or to ſettle thine eſtate? or regard thy mourning friends about thee? When thy pulſe is low, and thy breath ſhort, and thy Spirits almoſt gone, thy Sins many, and thy fears great, and thou haſt hardly Sufficient ſtrength to get rid of a clot of Spittle, is <hi>that</hi> a time to enter the liſts with <hi>Principalities and powers,</hi> and all the rulers of outer darkneſs? Beſide, 'tis the ſate of many, the nearer they approach to Death, that the leſs apt they are to believe it: and ſo periſh in their ſecurity, and are totally uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd about a future judgment.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing the free uſe of Reaſon, and an awaken'd
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30652:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>apprehenſion likewiſe of what refers to their Immortal Souls, and their Eternal abode. I then add:</p>
            <p n="5">5. That if, through the inticements of youthful luſts, you now neglect to prepare, it is very probable, and you may juſtly fear it, that <hi>your paſſage, by Death, to this Judgment of God will be very uncomfortable and full of horror:</hi> whether repentance on the brink of the Grave, after a a wicked life, may be Saving or no, is not the queſtion. Thro' an extraordinary act of Grace (whereof the penitent Theif was an inſtance) it cannot be deny'd poſſible: But when it is ſincere and ſaving, who can tell, any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than as in charity we muſt hope the beſt? For as to the <hi>perſons</hi> themſelves, on a ſick and deathbed, how can they in an <hi>Ordinary</hi> way be aſſured of their ſincerity? it is therefore probable, that their laſt Sickneſs will be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable, tho' their Repentance ſhould prove ſincere, and their Souls ſaved in the day of Chriſt. For ſuppoſe, when their ſins ſtare them in the face, and they did never till now bethink themſelves of the neceſſity of a pardon; That Satan ſhould now tell them, that their Repentance doth come too late to meet with that mercy they ſo long abus'd. And that 'tis all owing to their Fears of Death, and the apprehended dreadful conſequences of dying. If he ſhould tell 'em, that the pleaſures of Sin being loſt, and ſo the bait to intice them gone; every thing about them looks ſad and mournful; and ſuch a change of their condition, from health to ſickneſs, and the Gates of Death, muſt needs alter their reſolutions and thoughts. If he ſhould tell 'em, that the nearneſs of Eternity cannot but make a perſon, who hath ſpace to conſider, more appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of <hi>another World,</hi> and concerned about it, than at other times; and that if Sickneſs and Death were at a greater diſtance, they wuold ſtill be the ſame: which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30652:21"/>is to ſadly probable from the many Examples of thoſe, who have return'd to their <hi>former ſins,</hi> aſſoon as they return'd to their <hi>health;</hi> and left all their repentance, their holy thoughts, and good reſolutions, in that Sickbed, where at firſt they took 'em up. If the Devil ſuggeſt ſuch a Temptation as this to the Sick Penitent, who <hi>hath hitherto walk'd in the way of his own heart, and in the ſight of his Eyes,</hi> what can he reply, or plead on his own behalf, to make proof of the Sincerity of his Repentance to himſelf, or to thoſe about him? However, it may become us to conſider ſeriouſly, that God doth oftentimes in righteous Judgment open the Eyes of <hi>Great Sinners</hi> on a Death-bed; and fill their Souls with an amazing horror from the fears and foreſight of of his approaching vengeance. When they cannot but apprehend, that their Sinning ſeaſon is now expir'd; their mirth and jollity over; their final Judgment at hand; and their <hi>Bodies</hi> and <hi>Souls</hi> within a few hours to part, and ſo be divided between the <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> you will then admit other thoughts of God, and his terrible Judgment, than at preſent in your careleſs health: bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reflecting on your paſt follies, in the days of your Youth; and freely condemning your former choice: the ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of your venſual Joys, (which are fled as a ſhadow, and vaniſht like a cloud of ſmaok) ſhall give you an unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble remorſe and ſhame; having barter'd away your Souls for ſuch a thing of nought, and ventured your Eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a triſling luſt.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Was my God, my Soul, and my Salvation, of no greater value, will you then be forc'd ſay; of no greater value; than ſo eaſily to be parted with, for the ſhort ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of abrutiſh forbidden pleaſure? muſt I leave this world I lov'd ſo dearly? and bid adieu for ever to all its injoyments? are all my good days paſt? is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30652:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>all my mirth and joy concluded? and nothing but E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal ſorrows to be expected? muſt all my mirth and laughter be exchanged for tears and howling? my eaſe and pleaſure for inſuportable and remedileſs torments? muſt my guilty Soul be thus torn from my body? and from all things in which it took delight? to be drag'd and hurried to a diſmal place, where it will hate to live, and yet cannot dye? Muſt I ſport, and ſing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel it no more? Muſt I brave it out in Pride no longer? and reliſh the delights of ſenſe no more, no more, for ever?</p>
               <p>And which is worſe, infinitely worſe: muſt I make my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance before my offended Judge, whoſe threatnings I derided, whoſe wrath I provok't, whoſe commands I contradicted, whoſe ſervants I reproch't, &amp;c? muſt I now appear before the dreadful tribunal of this Juſt, this Holy, this Inexorable Judge? Is there no hope of eſcape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the crowd, and ſo avoid a trial? or is there no poſſibility of an excuſe, when arraigned before his bar? or is there no method to be found to evade the Execution of his Terrible Judgment? muſt I hear, and hear to my Confuſion, that Epitome of Hell compriz'd into a Sentence? <hi>Depart, Depart from me ye curſed into Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire?</hi> Oh! what ſhall I be able to ſay for my ſelf? when my own Conſcience brings the charge, and reads the Indictment, and I cannot diſown or deny one Article of what I am accus'd?</p>
            </q>
            <p>All the mercies you have receiv'd from God; all the inſtructive, afflictions you have at any time met with; all the awakening, Sermons you have heard, all the mot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>God's Spirit,</hi> and the rebukes of <hi>your own,</hi> which you have reſiſted; all the calls of his Word, the warnings of his Providence, and the threatnings of his Wrath, which you have ſlighted; your knowledg of your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30652:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>danger; your time and ſpace to repent, your former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Sin; your convictions of guilt; your purpoſes to reform; the reproofs you have had from others; and the promiſes you have made your ſelves; may all be muſter'd up to your awakn'd thoughts, to ſeize your Souls with horror and confuſion, when you are called by Death to paſs to this Judgment of God.</p>
            <p>And now, Chriſtians, 'tis probable you may ſuppoſe and hope that this will never be your caſe; yet the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent inſtance, of this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappy youth</hi> may convince you that 'tis poſſible, and more than poſſible. For tho' I never ſaw him (to my knowledg) Save on his Death-bed, yet having expreſt his own deſires, that others might take warning by his Example, I need not ſcruple to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you (with what I learn't from himſelf, and is well known to his Surviving companions.) that during his health, he did <hi>put the evil day far from him:</hi> and yet was very apprehenſive of a future Judgment, and concern'd at his own unpreparedneſs, in his laſt Sickneſs; moſt heartily confeſſing, and that with Tears, that he had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulged to youthful Luſts, delighted in wicked company, liv'd in the prophanation of the Sabbath, and made a mock of every thing almoſt that was Serious. And this notwithſtanding the counſels of his Friends, and ſome checks of his own Conſcience: ſadly bemoaning his forlorn ſtate, as having little or no hope to find mercy at the hand of God; and penitently confeſſing his own willfulneſs and folly that procur'd it to himſelf: and thereupon cry'd out in the bitterneſs of his Soul,
<q>Oh! had I believ'd and known, what now I do; I would have been more concerned to Secure my Everlaſting Intreſt; I would have taken more care to avoid Temptation; I would have imploy'd my Time to better purpoſes: and attended the miniſtry of the Word in another manner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:30652:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>I fear 'tis now too late.</q> And then with the greateſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity did beg of God to pardon and forgive him, for the ſake of Chriſt; then toſſing from place to place, wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hands, and lifting up his eyes to Heaven, (with the affecting vehemence of a deſpairing Soul) did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the aſſiſtance of thoſe about him to ſeek to God on his behalf.
<q>Oh pray for me, pray for me, for Chriſt's ſake pray for me; That if yet Mercy may be had, the Lord would take pitty on a miſerable Sinner. O my Sins are a burden too heavy for me to bear; I have Sin'd tho' God ſtood by and ſaw me: I have Sin'd tho' my Conſcience did rebuke me for it; again, I have Sin'd, tho' I reſolv'd to Sin no more; I know not what to do, or which way to turn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> for with ſuch words as theſe did he bewail himſelf, and ſignifie the horrors of an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing Conſcience. Nevertheleſs, for the ſupport of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and the encouragement of all returning Sinners, I am willing to add, That a little before his change (which was ſuddain and unexpected, when his Friends began to entertain ſome hopes of his recovery) his Spirit was more compos'd and calm, his diſtracting Terrors much abated; and the overwhelming fears of Death and Judgment very much ſubdu'd and overcome.</p>
            <p>In his confeſſions of ſin, he own'd and aggravated his crimes with the greateſt freedom, with a deep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe of Spirit, and an hearty ſerious ſenſe and feeling of what he ſpake. He did not go about to palliate or excuſe his former wickedneſs, to leſſen or diminiſh it, by ſhifting the blame on the ſubtilty of the Devil, the bias and inclination of a bodily Temper, the Corrupution of humane nature, or the perſuaſions of <hi>Evil Company, &amp;c.</hi> altho' <hi>this laſt</hi> he did very much lament, as the greateſt ſnare to his Soul, and a principal occaſion of his youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſins, and apprehended Ruine.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:30652:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Among other <hi>ſins</hi> which an accuſing Conſcience told him of, <hi>one</hi> that did more particularly affect his heart, and burden his soul, was the <hi>ſin of Lying;</hi> I mention this, with an unfeigned deſire, that all young Perſons (Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentices eſpecially) would remember this Example, and reſolve againſt it.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one thing more,</hi> which I named firſt, and would here take notice of, I mean <hi>his Scoffing Humour;</hi> and <hi>this</hi> he acknowledged with a great deal of remorſe and ſhame; that when firſt he was an hearer in this place, he came with a deſign to <hi>droll upon the Sermon,</hi> and <hi>deride the Preacher:</hi> But not meeting with any thing on which to break a Jeſt, or occaſion mirth and laughter, nothing but what was ſerious, becoming the reverence and awful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of holy things, and ſuited to the ſolemn work and ſervice of a Sabbath, he reſolv'd to come again, and accordingly for ſome time did ſo, (I cannot ſay how long) with other thoughts of my Brethren and me, and of the ſerious plainneſs of this our way of worſhip, than his former Ignorance and prejudices would ſuffer him to admit; and thanks be to God <hi>he is not the only Inſtance of this kind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I cannot but ſubjoyn, that as Religion is not the leſs excellent, becauſe ſome Fools deſpiſe it; nor ſin the leſs deſtructive, becauſe there be ſome Atheiſtical Scoffers who make a mock of ſin; neither is plain and ſerious Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (with the purity and ſimplicity of Goſpel-worſhiop) any whit the more Contemptible, becauſe ſome that <hi>ſit in the chair of Scorners,</hi> deride and run it down; ſince theſe kind of Scoffers are uſually ſuch as caſt off all thoughts of God and an after-reckoning, and are no way influenc'd by the conſideration of a future Life; to whom <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> are words of <hi>ſport,</hi> and the <hi>Sacred Scripture</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>deriſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:30652:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>For none, methinks, who are ſerious in the practice of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and make a conſcience of their words and actions, ſhould dare to make a mock of the <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or thoſe that joyn therein, whether Miniſters or people: only upon the account of ſome little difference, from that method and way of worſhip, which they like beſt, when the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> and deſign of <hi>both</hi> is apparently the ſame, and believ'd to be ſo. Did men but <hi>underſtand</hi> what they <hi>profeſs</hi> by owning Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; did they but <hi>believe</hi> what they <hi>underſtand;</hi> and <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> what <hi>they</hi> pretend to believe, a meer Reverence and Juſt regard to holy Things, would moſt certainly give a check to this <hi>Scoffing Humour,</hi> in reference to thoſe who cannot in all reſpects conform to their meaſures.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, <hi>Conſider the dreadfulneſs and the Terror of this final Judgment, in its ſelf, and its certain and immediate Conſequences to every unprepared ſinner, whether young or old.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the <hi>bleſſed Jeſus</hi> ſhall be revealed from Heaven, with his mighty Angels, to take the Throne by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's order, and Judge the World in righteouſneſs; when <hi>he</hi> that ſtoop'd from Heaven to Earth, to be a ſacrifice for ſin; that watcht, and pray'd, and ſweat drops of blood for you and me; that endured the Contradiction of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners againſt himſelf, in the days of his fleſh; ſuffer'd the Cruelty of men, and the Wrath of his Father, and the Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Death of the Croſs, upon our account; ſhall come again as the Judge of quick and dead; we ſhall then have other thoughts of him and of our ſelves, than now we entertain.</p>
            <p>Sirs, he <hi>now</hi> offers you a pardon, as the purchaſe of his Death, on eaſy, honourable, and advantageous terms; But it will be <hi>then</hi> too late, and in vain to beg it. He <hi>now</hi> warns you of your danger, and tells you, that the end of youthful luſts, is Death, and Judgment, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Wrath. And <hi>then</hi> you ſhall know that he ſpake in earneſt, and his words were true. <hi>Now</hi> as a merciful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30652:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>he entreats you to be reconcil'd; he ſhall <hi>then</hi> be clothed with vengeance, and appear, to your confuſion, as a Terrible Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>At firſt</hi> he came in the form of a Servant, to make our Peace with God, and was thereupon deſpiſed and rejected of men. But he <hi>ſhall</hi> ſhortly <hi>come again,</hi> to render ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to thoſe, that would not know him as a Prince and a Prophet, receive his meſſage, and yeild obedience to his Holy Goſpel. <hi>Now</hi> he offers life, eternal life, and begs your acceptance of it: but he will <hi>then</hi> revenge your ungrateful refuſal of his offered mercy. <hi>Now</hi> he entreats you to be happy, and have compaſſion on your ſelves: But <hi>then</hi> he will be as deaf to <hi>your entreaties,</hi> as you have been to <hi>his;</hi> and that, though you ſhould urge him with the greateſt importunity poſſible, though you beſeech him by the mercifulneſs of his Nature, by the freeneſs of his Invitation, by the Compaſſion of his Death, by the merit of his ſufferings, by the kindneſs of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, by the Grace of his Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c. Now</hi> you wil not believe his <hi>promiſes;</hi> but <hi>then</hi> you ſhall experience the execution of his <hi>Threatnings. Now</hi> you <hi>will not hearken</hi> to his advice and warning, but you <hi>ſhall ſhortly feel</hi> the ſad effects of your contempt and obſtinacy. <hi>Now</hi> you will not be conſtrained by his dying love; but ere long you ſhall know the power of his wrath, whether you will or no; for though at preſent he offer you life; yet upon your refuſal, he will ſhortly pronounce the Sentence of Eternal Death; <hi>as yet he</hi> Invites you to him, but <hi>then</hi> he will bid you depart. <hi>Depart from me, ye curſed, into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From that <hi>God,</hi> after whoſe Image you were Created, from that <hi>Saviour,</hi> who redeemed you by his blood, and from that <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> who would have ſanctified you by his Grace.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:30652:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Depart from me,</hi> and all hopes of Salvation by me. <hi>From me,</hi> and all the bleſſed Company of Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that ſhall live with me for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Depart from me,</hi> abandoned to an everlaſting curſe, (of which both Souls and bodies ſhall be the wretched unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Subjects) into <hi>Inquiſite Torments</hi> ſet forth by fire, and <hi>ſuch</hi> as were originally deſign'd for the <hi>Apoſtate Spirits,</hi> of <hi>whom</hi> the Scripture doth ſuppoſe one to be the principal Ring leader of all the reſt, and who are therefore termed his Angels.</p>
            <p>They who tempted you to Sin, ſhall deride your folly, and triumph in your Rain; and be your Conſtant perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Tormentors, ſince the <hi>fire is unquenchable, and never goeth out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, how dreadful ſoever this Sentence muſt needs be, it is not more intolerable in it ſelf, than unavoidable to the Sinner: For where will you hide from his Alſeeing eye? or how will you reſiſt the force of his Almighty arm? as it will be in vain to think of ſupporting his wrath: ſo every whit as vain to Imagine a poſſibility of eſcaping it. Will the tears of a deſparing Sinner extinguiſh the fire of Gods wrath, and quench the flames of Hell? will his wiſhing he had been wiſer, in the leaſt avail, when the Charge is proved, and the Sentence paſt? whither would you flee from the juſtice of the judge? whither? but to the mercy of a Saviour? But <hi>this Saviour</hi> is now the <hi>Judge,</hi> and become your <hi>Enemy:</hi> A ſight of <hi>whom</hi> ſhall awaken the moſt ſlumbering Conſcience, and make the never-dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worm gnaw your very heart: when it ſhall mind you of the calls and invitations you refuſed, and the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings you ſlighted, revive the convictons you ſtifled, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you of the vows you broke, and force you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on the vanities of your youth, and ſadly look back on the time paſt of your ignorance and folly.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:30652:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>When for a light temptation, you run the hazard of this heavy puniſhment; when for a temporal pleaſure you ventured an endleſs Torment; for a mixt delight, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed pain; for a momentary ſatisfaction, an eternal Wrath; for a ſhort Sin, an everlaſting Sorrow. O <hi>Eternity! Eternity!</hi> is it true, or rather can it poſſibly be falſe, that after millions of ages, under the wrath of God, it will not then be paſt the beginning of Sorrows, but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting vengeance will be yet to come, and will ever be to come. O curſed be my wicked Companions that inticed me to Sin, and ſo to ruine; or rather, Curſt be my own ſtupidity and folly, that I would not be perſwaded to believe what now I know and feel. Oh that I were now on Earth again, and had the benefit of one months ſpace, in order to a ſecond trial! Oh that I had never ſeen the light, or that the Earth had open'd and and ſwallowed me up in my Cradle! or rather, Oh that in <hi>time</hi> I had received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and harkened to reproof; that in <hi>time</hi> I had believed what <hi>I was</hi> told ſo plainly, and warned of ſo Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, concerning God and his Righteous Judgment.</p>
            <p>Now that this may never be the caſe of any one of us, let me conclude with the advice of the Prophet, Jer. 13.16. <hi>Give Glory to the Lord your God, before he cauſe dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and before your feet ſtumble upon the dark mountains, and while ye look for light, he turn it into the ſhadow of Death, and make it groſs darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:30652:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
